Guide to the Jean-Louis Barrault photograph collection, 1947-1979
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections Research Center, George Mason University
Jean-Louis Barrault photograph collection
1947-1979
George Mason University. Special Collections Research Center
Jenkins, Paul, 1923-
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Contains nearly 400 black and white photographs documenting Jean-Louis Barrault and Madeleine Renaud's career in the theatre in France between 1947 and 1979.
C0019
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Suzanne Donnelly Jenkins and Paul Jenkins, 2007.
Biographical Information
Barrault, born in France in 1910, was an esteemed and innovative fixture in French theatre and film for five decades from the 1930s to 1980s. He trained as a mime and an actor, and later directed both screen and stage productions. With Madeleine Renaud, his wife, he founded a theatrical company in Paris in 1947, after acting and directing with the Comedie Francaise. Barrault later directed the Theatre d'Orsay and the Theatre des Nations.
Scope and Content
The collection contains photographs documenting Barrault and Renaud's career in the theatre in France between 1947 and 1979. Most images are production stills of performances at the Theatre d'Orsay, Theatre de France Odeon, and other venues, but the collection also includes images of Barrault and his contemporaries off-stage. Madeleine Renaud is, after himself, the most frequently photographed. Samuel Beckett, Eugene Ionesco, and Jean Genet are among the notable theatrical figures documented.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series 1: Production Photographs, 1947-1979 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Non-Production Photographs, 1947-1976 (Box 2)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center holds several other notable collections on
Index Terms
Persons:
Barrault, Jean-Louis, 1910-1994--Photographs.; Renaud, Madeleine, 1900-1994--Photographs.
Corporate Names:
Agence de Presse Bernand.
Subjects:
Theater and society--France--Photographs.
Document Types:
Photographic prints.
Contents List
- Series 1: Production Photographs, 1947-1979; (2 boxes)
  Series 1 contains photographs from the collection dealing with specific theatrical productions and events. The photographs are organized alphabetically by production title and chronologically within each folder.
  - 65eme Anniversaire, September 8, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    3 photographs
  - Ainsi Parlait Zarathustra, November 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    13 photographs
  - Amphitryon, 1947-October 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    9 photographs
  - Andromaque, November 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    4 photographs
  - Bacchus, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baptiste, 1946-December 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    8 photographs
  - Christophe Colomb, October 1953-September 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    16 photographs
  - Conference Spectacles Claudel Dramaurgie, January 16, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2 photographs
  - Des Journees Entieres dans les Arbres, November 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Delicate Balance, November 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    6 photographs
  - Elisabeth d'Angleterre, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1 photograph
  - Gala Georges le Roy, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gala Jacques Copeau, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hamlet, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Harold et Maude, November 1973-October 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Il Faut Passar Par Les Nuages, October 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    5 photographs
  - Inauguration de la Place Paul Claudel, April 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Inauguration de nouveau plafond peintr par Andre Masson, November 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Inauguration du theatre d'Orsay, March 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jarry sur la Butte, October 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Jules Cesar, October 1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - La Cerisaie, December 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - La Lacune, February 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - La Mere, November 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - La Nuit a sa Clarte, October 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - La Petite Moliere, November 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - La Revelation, March 1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - La Seconde Suprise de L'Amour, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - La Tentation de Saint Antoine, March 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - La Vie Parisienne, November 1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    7 photographs
  - L'Amante Anglaise, February 1971-September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lazare, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme, December 1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Le Chien du Jardinier, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Le Dragon, June 1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Le Misanthrope, December 1954 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Le Partage de Midi, February 1949-September 1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    11 photographs
  - Le Personnage Combattant, January 1956-September 1971 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Le Piton de l'Air, January 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    14 photographs
  - Le Proces, January 1948-October 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    12 photographs
  - Le Songe Des Prisonniers, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Le Soulier de Satin, December 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Le Viol de Lucrece, January 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Le Voyage, February 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - L'change, December 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Les Fausses Confidences, 1946-December 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Les Fourberies de Scapin, February 1949-January 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Les Nuits Des Paris, December 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Les Paravents, April 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Les Suites d'une Course, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - L'etat de Siege, November 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - L'exposition de Paul Claudel, October 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - L'Orestie d'Eschyle, June 1954-January 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    10 photographs
  - Malatesta, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Malborough s'en va t el Guerre, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Numance, November 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Occupe Toi D'Amelie, November 1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Oh Les Beaux Jours, October 1963-February 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ou Boivent le Vaches, November 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Pour Lucrece, March 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Premier Anniversaire de l'Ouverture de Theatre d'Orsay, April 1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Rabelais, December 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rhinoceros, January 1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Tete d'Or, October 1959 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Theatre Kabuki de Tokyo, October 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Un Gala Moliere, December 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Un Otage, February 1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Un reception en l'honneur de Moiesseiv, October 1955 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Va et Vient, February 1966 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Volpone, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Wings, October 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Wozzeck, November 1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Zadig, October 1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series 2: Nonproduction Photographs, 1947-1976; (1 box)
  Series 2 contains the nonproduction photographs, such as publicity photographs, images of rehearsals, and pictures of playbills and signs. The photographs are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Rehearsal Photographs, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    5 photographs. This folder contains images of Barrault and other actors in rehearsal for various productions.
  - Playbills and Signs, 1958-November 1974 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    12 photographs. This folder contains photographs of signage and playbills for the productions of Barrault's company at various theaters.
  - Publicity Photographs, January 1948-October 25, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    15 photographs. This folder contains publicity photographs for various actors associated with Barrault and his productions, such as Barrault, Madeleine Renaud, and Marcel Marceau. Additionally, the folder contains images of a lecture given by Barrault about his production of Numance.